hi everybody welcome back to the next
episode in our chocolate series
today we are going to do a quick
comparison of cocoa powder versus
physical chocolate now as we mentioned
in the last episode i'll put a link to
that below or up here somewhere who
knows
we're going to use
urca coco powder which is 22 to 24
fat
and burema chocolate which is 56 fat not
barium chocolate has the autocorrect did
on the last video i'm pretty sure barium
would
not only taste really weird but
really be quite bad for you so let's not
make barium ice cream okay
so to make these recipes
we're going to make the fat content the
sugar content the solids and everything
approximately the same or as best as we
can we're going to use two different ice
cream calculators to do this we're going
to use dream scoops calculator for the
cocoa powder version and we're going to
use patrick svenson's ice cream
calculator for the chocolate one
not only is it the best ice cream
calculator there is out there it is the
only one that you can actually put real
chocolate in your calculations too so
we'll talk a bit about that as we do it
in real time so
recipes for both these are below they're
nice and simple we're not going to do
any add-ins or fudge swirls or cookie
dough or anything like that really plain
chocolate ice cream to compare the
results from two different
sources of chocolate and how they
compare whether one is stronger in
flavor whether one has a nicer chocolate
taste whether they're different in
texture all those kind of things so
stick with us and we'll get round and
get on to making them now
[Music]
we are going to start with the cocoa
powder version as mentioned we're going
to use the dream scoops calculator for
this when you first open a calculator
you can see at the top there are some
figures for milk and cream fat
percentage you're going to need to
change those for your own milk and cream
numbers then add in the fat percentage
of your cocoa powder in exactly the same
way working your way down the list
adding some numbers until you get a
basic recipe of some kind once you've
started you can see here at the bottom
the total fats milk solids non-fat
sugars and total solids you can just go
back and start editing these numbers
until you get something that's
reasonable
i've continued editing this and ended up
with something that is 17.9
fat 9.3 percent milk solids non-fat 18
sugars and 48
total solids
[Music]
now we move on to patrick svenson's
calculator when you open the software
you can click on the new and there are
some guidelines there if you want to use
them but as we're not going to go
anything really crazy we're not even
really going to produce a balanced
recipe here we're just going to produce
a recipe we'll start with new and blank
here we'll click add ingredient and then
work our way down through choosing the
milk that we want with the right fat
percentage and we'll do the same for the
cream
then you can move on and start adding in
your things like your sugar your
chocolate and finely finish on your
skimmed milk powder well that's how i'd
like to do it here now the chocolate
options are there you've got your milk
your your dark your semi-sweet and your
true dark all got the relevant macros in
there so make sure you add the right
right one now at this stage you can
double click on the wait box and start
inputting some figures as you can see
the software will assist and show you
the working numbers as you go the graph
or the bar graph in red shows areas that
might need adjustment now just keep
adding in your numbers and you can then
see down the line we look at total
sugars now this is one that i've added
myself it wasn't on there originally
patrick showed me how to add this bar i
find it quite helpful
all the other numbers in there can be
customized you can just click on this
button here add in whatever bit of
information you want and it will really
just be fully customizable to suit your
needs
each option here has a recommended level
written underneath so if you're not 100
sure on what it should be just use these
guidelines
now if you click on this graph this will
show you your freezing temperatures and
serving temperatures now
we're not going for a balance recipe
here this technically will go a little
bit harder than i like to make my ice
cream and that's just down to sugar
content really but we'll go through that
in another episode because this is quite
an exhaustive bit of
software and there's a lot here that you
can do
as a matter of interest gelato is
generally served at -12 centigrade
so we're just going to start editing the
numbers
until we get something that we're more
or less happy with if you really want to
add dextrose to a recipe again just to
add it add it as a separate ingredient
start adding some numbers that will have
a real effect on your serving
temperature how hard your ice cream goes
because it's not as sweet as a sucrose
but it affects the freezing point much
much more so dextrose is really a great
ingredient for ice cream makers
anyway we're not going to use it in this
recipe so we're just going to remove
that
and we're left with a base recipe here
we're just going to adjust this back to
where it was
and that's pretty much where we're going
to end up
now this is another fun bit you can
actually rescale your recipes here once
you're happy with the recipe you can put
in the total that you actually want to
make and the software will calculate it
all for you so you don't actually do you
don't have to go old school and do maths
or if you're in north america math
um
the calculator will do it all for you
you can make large recipes smaller
recipes whatever suits your machine
most people generally try and work
around a one liter size base and then
you can just halve it double it whatever
you need to do this will be exact if you
know your machine does really well with
a 1.2 liter worth of base in there start
a recipe and then adjust using that
method and it will work it all out for
you
once you're happy with that you can then
save it to use later on
and what we've ended up with here is a
recipe that is 18.8 fat 9.6 milk salad
is non-fat 17.8 sugar
42.5
solids
so we're not going to discuss how to
make these bases they're really simple
you've seen me do it hundreds of times
just heat these up on your hob enough to
melt the sugars and the cocoa powder and
the chocolate depending on which one
you're doing for the cocoa powder keep
that up to temperature for a good five
minutes just to bloom the cocoa powder
and bring that flavor out more if you're
making the physical chocolate version
make sure it's completely melted it will
get to a stage where it looks very bitty
you have to keep going past that until
it turns nice and smooth once it's done
put them both in the fridge to chill
churn them as normal and let's get
scooping
right just taken both these ice creams
out of freezer we're gonna get some
scooped
and compare the two
[Music]
so there's both in front of you i mean
it's quite clearly
a different
effect based on what you use so the one
on the left is the cocoa powder the one
on the right is the physical chocolate
now with the recipes uh identical or
give or take fat contents
you run into some problems because
there's no way to get the chocolate
flavor with the physical chocolate or
the same amount of physical chocolate as
you would do a cocoa powder remember
cocoa powder is just intensified
chocolate essentially that's what it is
so how does it taste
[Music]
two very different ice creams
now interestingly
this one which is the physical chocolate
there's 56 chocolate
it has the flavor of the chocolate
itself come through and it does come
through reasonably well but also you've
got basically no color
as you can see the color of the physical
chocolate has just completely gone and
that's because you've melted the
chocolate the dairy has overtaken it and
essentially that's all they do when they
create milk chocolate they take a darker
chocolate and add more milk to it that's
what you do when you create chocolate so
you've taken a 56 chocolate and brought
it right the way down to i dread to
think of how low this would be as far as
chocolate numbers is concerned
and something also to point out is
the chocolate itself in this
has started to freeze back together as
the ice cream has been made so it's
almost giving you a really fine
strategella kind of effect and that's
more likely because although chocolate
has an emulsifier and i think this one
uses soy lecithin
it's obviously not enough
to emulsify the chocolate within the
dairy mix itself so it starts to come
back together because the cocoa powder
it's a different puppy altogether it
dissolves into your mix as long as you
heat it up properly dissolves into your
mix and becomes part of your dairy mix
so
texture-wise
they're the same there's no real
difference there's no iciness to one or
the other they're very simple recipes so
that you can't really go wrong with
these two
they're not gonna break the bank as far
as luxurious chocolate ice creams go but
that's not the point of this this is to
show the real world difference between
using physical chocolate and cocoa
powder
now
cocoa powder
isn't all created equally there are good
there are bad there are ugly and
indifferent
my personal favorite is valrona
it's also the most expensive cocoa
powder that i know of
but
erka does a really good job there are
some really nice ones calabar do a nice
cocoa powder as well
it's lighter in flavor lighter in color
you know so there are pros and cons for
each one like we mentioned before
physical chocolate now we'll do this in
another episode but to get this kind of
color with physical chocolate
is impossible because by the time you
melt the chocolate add it to the dairy
it lightens up in color like this 56 has
more likely become somewhere in the
single digits as far as
milk chocolate is concerned so if we
used 100 chocolate
what would the effect be maybe we'll do
that in in the next episode
but cocoa powders you could use any
cocoa powder going even the cheapest one
and you'll get something
reasonably similar color wise that it
differs depending on whether it's dutch
cocoa or not whether it's a heavily
dutched cocoa
heavily dutched cocoa has an effect on
the color as well so the more dutch that
is which means treated with alkaline
solution the darker it can become as
well but profile of flavor changes at
the same time so
if you really want bang for buck you
just can't beat cocoa powder so next
episode
we'll
make a couple of different chocolate ice
creams we'll probably make
a combination so one that uses cocoa
powder and physical chocolate and then
we'll try a different cocoa powder just
on its own and see how they compare
anyway i hope you enjoyed this next
episode in our chocolate series if
you're interested in the ins and outs of
chocolate ice cream don't forget to like
and subscribe and we'll see you next
week
[Music]
you